Finding Aid for Alexander Winchell Papers, 1833-1891
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alexander Winchell Papers 1833-1891
Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.
1 oversize folders
23.5 linear feet (in 25 boxes)
86321 Aa 2 AC
Professor of geology and paleontology at the University of Michigan, director of the Michigan Geological Survey, and chancellor of Syracuse University, popular lecturer and writer on scientific topics and as a Methodist layman who worked to reconcile traditional religious beliefs to nineteenth-century developments in the fields of evolutionary biology, cosmology, geology, and paleontology. Papers include extensive diaries, field notes and maps from travels and geological expeditions, correspondence, speeches, articles and other publications and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was donated in 1937 by the Minnesota Historical Society (donor 150 ), which in turn received it in 1931 from Mr. and Mrs. I. Robert Campbell of Minneapolis. Smaller portions were received in 1936 from Alexander Newton Winchell (donor 28 ) and in 1991 from the University of Minnesota, University Archives (donor 7957 ).
The collection is open for research.
Most of Winchell's papers relating to Syracuse University have been microfilmed, and are cataloged separately in the MHC catalog. A small subset of those records, with the addition of Winchell's list of publications, was microfilmed in a separate order. Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed are annotated as (microfilmed) or (microfilmed in part).
Alexander Winchell was professor of geology and paleontology at the University of Michigan, director of the Michigan Geological Survey, and chancellor of Syracuse University, but he was most noted as a popular lecturer and writer on scientific topics and as a Methodist layman who worked to reconcile traditional religious beliefs to nineteenth-century developments in the fields of evolutionary biology, cosmology, geology, and paleontology.
Winchell was born December 31, 1824, in the town of North East, Dutchess County, New York. After studying medicine and teaching school as a teenager, he entered Amenia Seminary, also in Dutchess County, in the fall of 1842. In 1844 he enrolled at Wesleyan University, from which he graduated in 1847. Over the following years Winchell held a succession of teaching positions at Pennington Male Seminary in New Jersey, Amenia Seminary, Newbern Academy in Alabama, Mesopotamia Female Seminary in Eutaw, Alabama, and Masonic University in Selma, Alabama.
Masonic University opened its doors in the fall of 1853, with Winchell as president. Unfortunately a yellow fever epidemic forced the school to close shortly thereafter, and Winchell accepted an offer of the chair in physics and civil engineering at the University of Michigan. Two years later his appointment was changed to the chair in geology, zoology, and botany.
By the time Winchell arrived at the University of Michigan, he had already begun his output of scientific publications, beginning with "Solar Spots," published in the New York Tribune, November 5, 1849. Winchell was a prolific writer: his bibliography contains 565 works.
While teaching at the University of Michigan, Winchell lobbied for the revival of the Michigan Geological Survey, which had expired after the death of Douglass Houghton, the first state geologist, in 1845. In 1859 the legislature reestablished the survey. Winchell was appointed state geologist, while keeping his position at the University of Michigan. Winchell's survey concentrated on the geology of the Lower Peninsula, which coincided with his interest in the fossils found in the sedimentary rocks underlying that part of the state. A progress report was published in 1861 (
First Biennial Report of the Progress of the Geological Survey of Michigan, MHC call number EA/153/MG345/F527
). With the outbreak of the Civil War in 1861, the legislature discontinued funding for the survey, and officially disbanded it in 1863.
The Civil War brought Winchell an opportunity to return to the South for a time. In 1863 he took up a lease on a cotton plantation near Vicksburg, Mississippi, that had been seized from rebels. The venture brought him nothing but problems, however, and after Winchell returned to Michigan in 1864, his brother Martin, who was managing the plantation, was killed by guerrillas.
It was during the 1860s that Winchell seems to have developed his most original geological theory. Private surveys of a number of oil-producing areas resulted in Winchell's exposition of the anticlinal reservoir theory of petroleum storage, which was proven and developed further by others in later years.
Also in the 1860s Winchell first described the lake effect which moderates the climate of western Michigan, making the region suitable for orchard development. This discovery came as a result of a private survey of the Grand Traverse Bay region of Michigan.
By 1869, the Michigan legislature was once again prepared to fund the Geological Survey, and Winchell was appointed director of the survey. Winchell's plan for a comprehensive survey of the resources of the state was described in
Report on the Progress of the State Geological Survey of Michigan, published in 1871 (MHC call number DB/2/W759/M678/Set B/v. 1),
but he never completed the task. After disputes with the Geological Survey board and with the legislature, Winchell resigned his position with the survey in 1871.
Winchell kept his teaching position at the University of Michigan until 1873, when he was named the first chancellor of Syracuse University. Disappointed with the position, Winchell resigned the following year, but remained at Syracuse as professor of geology.
In 1876, Winchell accepted a position as professor of geology and zoology at Vanderbilt University, but was fired in 1878 in a dispute over the teaching of evolution. Shortly thereafter Winchell returned to the University of Michigan, where he remained, as professor of geology and paleontology, until his death in 1891.
The relationship between science and religion was an interest of Winchell's beginning at least in the late 1850s, when he published Theologico-Geology, or, The Teachings of Scripture Illustrated by the Conformation of the Earth's Crust, and Voices from Nature: Creation the work of One Intelligence and not the Product of Physical Forces (both in MHC call number DB/2/W759/M678/Set B/v. 4). His work in this area expanded in the late 1860s, when Winchell began to tour, giving popular lectures on scientific topics. In 1869, while Winchell was directing the Geological Survey and teaching at the university, he also gave 48 public lectures in 5 states.
Winchell's thinking on the relationship between science and religion was affected by the debate over Darwinism that raged in American scientific circles after the publication of On the Origin of Species in 1859. Winchell was never a Darwinist, but by the 1870s he seems to have accepted evolution without accepting the theory of natural selection.
Two topics seem to have given Winchell much trouble in his attempts to reconcile his scientific knowledge with his religious faith: the age of the earth and the origin of the human race. Winchell's geological and paleontological research convinced him of the great age of the earth, which he tried to reconcile to the seven days of the Genesis creation story by making each day of creation represent an epoch of great length. In describing the history of the human race, also, Winchell could not reconcile the age of humanity, as revealed by archeological discoveries and explained by evolutionary theory, with biblical chronology and genealogy. Winchell solved this problem by suggesting the Adam was not the first human, but that Africans and other non-whites had evolved separately and were living before Adam was created. This solution caused various difficulties, and was the immediate cause of Winchell's firing from Vanderbilt University.
Among other organizations in which Winchell was active, he was president of the Michigan State Teachers Association in 1858 and editor of the Michigan Journal of Education in 1859; an organizer of the University Musical Society of the University of Michigan and the Choral Union in 1879 and 1880; an organizer of the Geological Society of America in 1888 and its president in 1890.
Winchell married Julia F. Lines of Utica, New York, December 5, 1849. They had six children, only two of whom survived Winchell. Alexander Winchell died February 19, 1891, in Ann Arbor.
The collection is divided into six major and three minor series:
Biographical
Correspondence
Diaries and journals
Writings and lectures
Reference and research files
Scrapbooks
Visual Materials
Processing notes
Card file
The papers of Alexander Winchell are those of an orderly man who carefully documented his own life through well-organized correspondence, diaries, notebooks, and scrapbooks. Winchell kept thorough evidence of his activities, writings, lectures, and thoughts, for most of his life. The only area that seems poorly documented is his university teaching. The collection does not appear to include significant material relating to relationships with students in the classroom.
"Alexander Winchell, an editorial tribute," published in The American Geologist (Feb. 1892, MHC call number DB/2/W759/A512)
, includes a year-by-year account of Winchell's life, based on the papers, and probably written by his brother N. H. Winchell. Although there are no footnotes in this work, it provides a useful summary of Winchell's activities and clues to the existence of documentation in the collection.
The collection is divided into six major series: Biographical, Correspondence, Diaries and journals, Writings and lectures, Reference and research files, and Scrapbooks; and three smaller series: Visual materials, Processing notes, and Card files.
Winchell's bibliography is located in Box 1 (the most complete copy is in the "Permanent memoranda" volume), and drafts of many of his writings are found in Boxes 8-14. Copies of many, but not all, of Winchell's publications are found in the MHC printed collection. The card catalog includes details for all separately cataloged items. There are also three collections of pamphlets that are not inventoried: two slightly different bound sets prepared by N. H. Winchell after Alexander Winchell's death (MHC call numbers DA/2/W759/M678/Set A and DA/2/W759/M678/Set B) and a two-box collection of pamphlets collected by the University Library (MHC call number Univ. of Mich. Coll./J/17/W759).
Subject terms
Alabama.; Amenia Seminary (Dutchess County, N.Y.); Ann Arbor (Mich.); Botany.; Education--United States.; Evolution--Religious aspects.; Fossils.; Geology--Michigan.; Grand Traverse Bay Region (Mich.); Human beings--Origin.; Meteorology.; Michigan--Climate.; Michigan--Geography.; Michigan. Geological survey.; Michigan State Teachers' Association.; Mississippi.; Natural history.; New York (State); Paleontology.; Religion and science.; Scientific expeditions--United States.; Syracuse University.; Voyages and travels.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Botany.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Geology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Zoology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. University Museum.; University of Michigan. University Musical Society.; Vanderbilt University.; Weather--Michigan.; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.; Winchell family.; Geology--United States.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Fossils.; Geology.; Photographs.; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.; Whitfield, C. P.; Winchell, N. H. (Newton Horace), 1839-1914.
Subjects - Maps:
Alcona County (Mich.)--Maps.; Alpena County (Mich.)--Maps.; Delta County (Mich.)--Maps.; Genesee County (Mich.)--Maps.; Grand Traverse County (Mich.)--Maps.; Hillsdale County (Mich.)--Maps.; Jackson County (Mich.)--Maps.; Lenawee County (Mich.)--Maps.; Mackinac County (Mich.)--Maps.; Manistee County (Mich.)--Maps.; Monroe County (Mich.)--Maps.; Presque Isle County (Mich.)--Maps.; Schoolcraft County (Mich.)--Maps.; Shiawassee County (Mich.)--Maps.; Washtenaw County (Mich.)--Maps.; Alabama--Maps.; Minnesota--Maps.; New York (State)--Maps.; Ohio--Maps.; Ontario--Maps.; West Virginia--Maps.; Geology--Michigan--Maps.; Geology--Minnesota--Maps.
Contributors
Agassiz, Alexander, 1835-1910.; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873.; Andrews, Edmund, 1824-1904.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887.; Ball, John, 1794-1884.; Chamberlin, Thomas C. (Thomas Chrowder), 1843-1928.; Chandler, Zachariah, 1813-1879.; Cocker, Benjamin Franklin, 1821-1883.; Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Cope, E. D. (Edward Drinker), 1840-1897.; Cummings, Joseph, 1817-1890.; Currier, A. O.; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895.; Dolbear, A. E. (Amos Emerson), 1837-1910.; Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1831-1881.; Hall, James, 1811-1898.; Harrington, Mark Walrod, 1848-1926.; Haven, E. O. (Erastus Otis), 1820-1881.; Haven, Gilbert, 1821-1880.; Headley, C. B.; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878.; Herrick, C. L. (Clarence Luther), 1858-1904.; Hitchcock, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1836-1919.; Marcy, Oliver, 1820-1899.; Meek, Fielding Bradford, 1817-1876.; Newberry, J. S. (John Strong), 1822-1892.; Safford, James Merrill, 1822-1907.; Silliman, Benjamin, 1816-1885.; Steere, Joseph Beal, 1842-1940.; Stevenson, John James, 1841-1924.; Strong, Edwin Atson, 1834-1920.; Tappan, Henry Philip, 1805-1881.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Wadsworth, A. S.; Ward, Lester Frank, 1841-1913.; Watson, James C. (James Craig), 1838-1880.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; White, Charles A. (Charles Abiathar), 1826-1910.; Whitfield, C. P.; Winchell, N. H. (Newton Horace), 1839-1914.
Genre terms
Diaries.; Maps.; Poetry.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Biographical, 0.5 linear feet
  The Biographical series contains several autobiographical writings, lists of publications, genealogical materials, and a volume entitled "Permanent memoranda," in which Winchell summarized his life by tabulating his publications, new species described, income, public lectures, and other benchmarks.
  - Biographical sketch and Will 1848, circa 1867 (Box 1)
    (microfilmed in part)
  - Biographical sketch 1886, 3 folders (Box 1)
    (microfilmed)
  - Genealogical charts and notes (Box 1)
  - Lists of AW publications (Box 1)
    [see also list in Permanent memoranda volume, Box 18]
  - Memberships (Box 1)
  - Obituaries (Box 1)
  - Permanent memoranda 1843-1891 (Box 1)
    [includes bibliography of Winchell's publications]
  - Reminiscences of Amenia Seminary, 1885 (Box 1)
  - School reports (Box 1)
  - Tears over the tomb: Recollections of my little angel child 1860, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Winchell family clippings (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (Boxes 1-5 and 25) includes a mixture of personal and business correspondence. The loose correspondence (Boxes 1-3) is chiefly incoming, with a few drafts of outgoing letters. Box 3 contains some incoming correspondence that has been separated from the general chronological series, most of it concerning the Michigan Geological Survey. Outgoing correspondence is located in the letterpress books in Boxes 3-5. A register of correspondence is found in Box 8. A card file of selected correspondents is found in the MHC reading room. (Ask the reference archivist for details.) In the Processing notes series (Box 23) are found biographical notes about many of Winchell's correspondents, made by Historical Records Survey processors.
  Note that Winchell sometimes cut autographs off of incoming letters. If text is missing it may be possible to reconstruct some of these letters from the autograph file in Box 14.
  - Card index to correspondence (Box 25)
  - Loose correspondence
    - 1840-1863, 29 folders (Box 1)
    - 1864-1889, 38 folders (Box 2)
    - 1890-1891, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Undated and unsigned (Box 3)
    - 1851-1854 (Box 3)
      (memoranda of correspondence with S. F. Baird)
    - 1882-1887 (Box 3)
      (of S.C. Griggs & Co., concerning Winchell's publications)
    - 1850-1889 (Box 3)
      (not addressed to Winchell)
  - Bound correspondence
    - 1869-1872, 3 volumes (Box 3)
      (chiefly concerning Michigan Geological Survey)
      [former v. 165-167]
    - 1871-1872 (Box 3)
      (of Jennie Winchell)
      [former v. 168]
    - 1858-1869 (Box 3)
      [former v. 154]
    - 1869-1886, 8 volumes (Box 4)
      [former v. 155-162] (microfilmed in part)
    - 1886-1891, 2 volumes (Box 5)
      [former v. 163-164]
  - Typescript of selected correspondence 1848-1863 (Box 5)
    [former v. 282]
  - Register of correspondence 1851-1891, 8 volumes (Box 5)
    [former v. 170-172, 174-177, and unnumbered] (microfilmed in part)
  - Register of publications mailed 1862-1878, 1881-1890; 2 volumes (Box 5)
    [former v. 173 and 236]
  - Addresses, 2 volumes (Box 5)
    [former v. 247-248]
- Diaries and journals
  The Diaries and journals series (Boxes 6-7) contains several different types of records, with different amounts and types of information. The series is divided into "Diaries," "Pocket diaries," "Travel diaries" and "Field diaries,"
  - Diaries, 1841-1868
    The "diaries" for the period 1841-1868 include substantial accounts of daily experiences, thoughts, and reflections.
    - 1841-1845, 1 folders (Box 6)
    - 1846-1848 (Box 6)
      (titled Hemerologion)
      [former v. 73]
    - 1848-1850 (Box 6)
      [former v. 75]
    - 1851-1852 (Box 6)
      (titled Business journal)
      [former v. 76]
    - 1853-1859 (Box 6)
      [former v. 78]
    - 1860-1864 (Box 6)
      [former v. 80a]
    - 1864-1866 (Box 6)
      [former v. 83]
    - 1866-1868 (Box 6)
      (former v. 85]
  - Pocket diaries, 1864-1865; 1867-1891; including 2 v. for 1874; 28 volumes (Box 6)
    [former v. 81, 84, 86, 88-91, 93-113] (microfilmed in part)
    The "pocket diaries" for the period 1864-1891 (missing 1866) include brief notations of daily activities.
  - Travel diaries, 1858-1873
    The "travel diaries" (Boxes 6-7) include two types of writings: Winchell's extended accounts of his travels away from his family, written for their information, and his accounts of travels taken by the rest of his family without him, based on their letters, perhaps written to ease his separation from them.
    - 1858 July 6-28 (Box 6)
      [former v. 79]
    - 1860 June 13-July 30 (Box 6)
      [former v. 80]
    - 1867-1886 (Box 7)
      titled Days of absence
      [former v. 87]
    - 1871 July 14-1872 May 26 (Box 7)
      (titled Via Carissimae, or, Days of absence of my darling Jennie)
      [former v. 92]
    - 1873 August 28-1874 July 14 (Box 7)
      (titled Dies Irae)
      [former v. 169] (microfilmed)
  - Typescript of extracts from diaries 1853-1859, 1862-1863 (Box 7)
    [duplicate of former v. 283]
  - Field books, 1852-1887
    The "field books" (Box 7) for 1852-1891 (not all years represented) include notes of geological and other scientific observations made both during Winchell's expeditions and in his daily life. This group also includes journals of his journey to Mississippi in 1863-1864 to manage his plantation. For the period 1859-1860 Winchell transcribed his field books relating to the Michigan Geological Survey into a large volume, which also is located in Box 7. (Field notes of Winchell's associates in the Michigan Geological Survey are located in Box 16.)
    - 1852 (Box 7)
      [former v. 77]
    - 1852-1866 (Box 7)
      (Chemical journal)
    - 1853-1865 (Box 7)
      (v. A)
    - 1854-1855 (Box 7)
      (Engineering survey book, v. 8)
    - 1856-1863 (Box 7)
      (Bee book)
    - 1859 (Box 7)
      (v. 5)
    - 1859-1860, 2 folders (Box 7)
      (5 v.: Geological Survey, v. 1, 3, 5-7)
    - 1862 (Box 7)
      (Private work, v. 9)
    - 1862 (Box 7)
      (Localities, v. 10)
    - 1865 (Box 7)
      (3 v.: Plantation business)
    - 1865 (Box 7)
      (Private work Grand Traverse Region, v. 13)
    - 1866, 1869 (Box 7)
      (Private work, v. 15)
    - 1867 (Box 7)
      (Expedition to Lake Superior, v. 16)
    - 1867-1868 (Box 7)
      (Excursion to New England, v. 18) [former v. 223]
    - 1873-1891 (Box 7)
      (40 v.: v. 27-66) (10 folders)
      [former v. 114-153] (microfilmed in part)
    - 1886-1887 (Box 7)
      (2 v.: Geological survey of Minnesota)
  - Handwritten transcription of field books April 1, 1859-1866 (Box 7)
    (Michigan Geological Survey)
    [former v. 180]
    [this volume also contains transcriptions of field notes of A. D. White]
- Writings and lectures
  The Writings and lectures series (Boxes 8-14) includes drafts of articles, book chapters, and lectures, and outlines for books and lectures. (Drafts that were identical to published works located in the MHC printed collection were not retained in this series.) The writings are arranged chronologically. The series also contains a group of volumes entitled "Notebooks," in which Winchell copied the text of many of his publications. The notebooks are grouped under three topics: "General" or "General geology," "Michigan" and "Popular." The series ends with two volumes and one folder of Winchell's poetry (Box 14). The writings are arranged chronologically.
  - miscellaneous 1833-1842, undated (Box 8)
  - Addition of federal money (Winter) 1837-1838 (Box 8)
  - miscellaneous 1839-1844, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - miscellaneous 1844-1847, undated (Box 8)
  - miscellaneous 1845-1846, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1847, 1 folders
    - Revolutions inevitable (Box 8)
      (July 3)
    - Is the world growing worse? (Box 8)
      (July 9)
    - Modern classical oration: the dayspring of Italian literature (Box 8)
      (Wesleyan University, July 27)
    - Some of the evidences of Christianity (Box 8)
      (Pennington, Sept. 5)
    - The Science of electricity (Box 8)
      (Pennington, Oct.)
  - 1848, 2 folders
    - [four lectures on astronomy] (Box 8)
      (Pennington, Jan. 27-Mar. 15; Amenia, Sept. 28-Nov. 16)
    - Lecture on infidelity (Box 8)
      (Amenia, Sept. 17)
    - Lecture on Morse's telegraph (Box 8)
      (2 different lectures, undated)
    - Whether there is any difference in the quality of music written sharp and flat keys, Undated (Box 8)
  - 1849 (Box 8)
    [Independence Day address]
  - 1850, 1 folders
    - [Independence Day address] (Box 8)
      (Amenia)
    - Gravity a condition of fluidity (Box 8)
      (New Haven, Aug. 20)
  - 1851, 1 folders
    - Editorial for The Chrysalis (Box 8)
      (July)
    - On barometrical observations as a means of detecting and measuring aerial tides (Box 8)
      (Mesopotamia, July 25,)
  - 1852
    - "Women's Rights a dialogue (Box 8)
      (Mesopotamia, July 9)
  - 1853, 1 folders
    - Conditions and prospects of our schools: addressed to the thinking people of Alabama (Box 8)
      (Masonic University, undated)
    - The Gar pike (Box 8)
      (May 25)
  - 1854, 1 folders
    - Civil engineering: introductory lecture (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, Feb. 10)
    - On rail road curves (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, Summer)
    - On dials and dialing (Box 8)
      (Nov.)
    - On the true relation of science and revelation (Box 8)
      (2 lectures, Methodist Church, Ann Arbor, Dec. 3 and Dec. 24)
    - Investigation of a new form of wind vane and anemometer (Box 8)
      (Dec.?)
  - 1855, 2 folders
    - Investigations, formulae, problems and solutions in mechanics (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, undated)
    - On the practical relations of abstract science (Box 8)
      (Salem, Mich., Feb. 9)
    - To the correspondents of the Northwestern Society of Natural History (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, May 23)
    - The great work of Prof. Agassiz (Box 8)